Guide to the Paul Kagan Photographs of Utopian Communities and Personal Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Paul Kagan photographs of utopian communities and personal papers
1895-1989
1968-1976
WA MSS S-2640
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4
(23 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
Chiefly photographs created and copied by Kagan while conducting research for his book, New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community. The photographs document nineteenth- and twentieth-century utopian communities, most located in California, with others in New Mexico, Pennsylvania, and Tennessee. The collection includes material that Kagan collected about utopian communities, including audiotapes of interviews and related events, as well as drawings and photographs. The collection also includes examples of photography and graphic design that Kagan created for traditional and alternative newspapers, as well as examples of some of his book reviews and other writings. A small group of material documents social action at the University of California, Berkeley, and in the San Francisco Bay area during the 1960s. Utopian communities and other groups represented in the collection include an unidentified Amish community, Ananda Ashrama, Caspar Compound, Divine Light Mission, Esoteric Fraternity, The Farm, Fundación Indra Devi, Fountaingrove, Fountain of the World, Halcyon, Holy City, Icaria Speranza, Kaweah Colony, Krotona (including Happy Valley School), Lama Foundation, Lemurian Fellowship, Llano del Rio, The Lord's Land, Pisgah Faith Home, Pisgah Grande, Point Loma, Rosicrucian Fellowship, Questhaven Retreat, Self-Realization Golden World Colony, Table Mountain Ranch, Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, Theosophical Society (Pasadena), Unification Church, and Vedanta Temple (Santa Barbara).
Kagan, Paul, 1943-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Sue Kagan on the Frederick W. & Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 18-19: Copy photographs are for reference use only, and are not to be reproduced. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 20 (audiocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies are available in Box 20. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Paul Kagan Utopian Communities Collection (WA MSS S-1737)
Walter Millsap / Keikichi Akana Imamura Family Papers (WA MSS S-1590)
Biography
Paul Kagan, photographer and author of the book New World Utopia s, was born in 1943. After receiving a degree in history from the University of California at Berkeley in 1965, he worked as a television news writer, photographer, graphic artist, and magazine art director. Kagan spent five years researching New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community (New York: Penguin Books, 1975). Initially, the National Institute of Mental Health provided funds for Kagan to photograph the remains of California 'utopias'; a few years into the project the California Historical Society gave him funds to research and collect the records and contemporary photographs of those communities. During this time Kagan organized the Utopian Studies Center at the California Historical Society Library (San Francisco). At the time of the book's publication, Kagan described himself as writer/researcher and still photographer for the Television Health Information Project at University of California Medical Center, San Francisco. Paul Kagan died in New York in 1993.
Scope and Contents
Chiefly photographs created and copied by Kagan while conducting research for his book, New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community (New York: Penguin Books, 1975). The photographs document nineteenth and twentieth century utopian communities, most located in California, with others in New Mexico, Pennsylvania, and Tennessee. The collection includes material he collected about utopian communities, including audiotapes of interviews and related events, as well as drawings and photographs. The collection also includes examples of photography and graphic design that Kagan created for traditional and alternative newspapers, as well as examples of some of his book reviews and other writings. A small group of material documents social action at the University of California, Berkeley, and in the San Francisco Bay Area during the 1960s.
Utopian communities and other groups represented in the collection include an Amish community, Ananda Ashrama, Caspar Compound, Divine Light Mission, Esoteric Fraternity, The Farm, Fundación Indra Devi, Fountaingrove, Fountain of the World, Halcyon, Holy City, Icaria Speranza, Kaweah Colony, Krotona (including Happy Valley School), Lama Foundation, Lemurian Fellowship, Llano del Rio, The Lord's Land, Pisgah Faith Home, Pisgah Grande, Point Loma, Rosicrucian Fellowship, Questhaven Retreat, Self-Realization Golden World Colony, Table Mountain Ranch, Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, Theosophical Society (Pasadena), Unification Church, and Vedanta Temple (Santa Barbara).
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Photographs of Utopian Communities, 1968-1976. II. Other Material Related to Utopian Communities, circa 1895-circa 1989. III. Personal Papers, 1960-circa 1989.
Amish -- Pictorial works; Christian communities -- California; Collective settlements -- California; Communal living; Communal living -- California; Communal living -- New Mexico; Communal living -- Pennsylvania; Communal living -- Tennessee; Cooperative societies -- California; Socialism -- California; Theosophy -- California; Underground periodicals; Utopias -- History -- 19th century; California -- Pictorial works; Fountaingrove (Calif.) -- Pictorial works; Halcyon (Calif.) -- Pictorial works; Happy Valley (Calif.) -- Pictorial works; Holy City (Calif.) -- Pictorial works; Icaria-Speranza (Collective settlement) -- Pictorial works; Pisgah Grande (Calif.) -- Pictorial works; San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.); Photographic prints; Kagan, Paul, 1943-; Fundacion Indra Devi; Happy Valley School; Divine Light Mission; Kaweah Colony; Krotona Institute of Theosophy (Ojai, Calif.); Lama Foundation; Lemurian Fellowship (Organization); Llano Colony (Secular community); Pisgah Home Movement; Point Loma Theosophical Society; Rosicrucian Fellowship; Tassajara Zen Mountain Center; Unification Church; University of California, Berkeley
- Photographs of Utopian Communities, 1968-1976; Series I; 3.38; (19 boxes)
  Arrangement
  This series is organized into three subseries: Photographs by Kagan, Oversize Photographic Prints by Kagan, and Copy Photographs.
  Scope and Contents
  This series mainly consists of photographic materials created by Kagan in the course of researching New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community. A small group of photographs from unidentified sources is also available in Series II. Other Material Related to Utopian Communities.
  - Photographs by Kagan
    Organized into two subseries: Notebook and Original Images by Kagan.
    This subseries chiefly consists of photographic negatives, contact sheets, and work prints created by Kagan related to utopian communities. Many of the photographs document the ruins or former sites of communities.
    Kagan visited some sites more than once. Some rolls of negatives document multiple sites and have been filed together to reflect the rolls.
    The subseries also includes a notebook by Kagan that provides background for some of the images, as well as material he copied from others.
    - Notebook, 1972 January-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Spiral-bound notebook with notes about photographs created by Kagan and copied by him, as well as research notes about utopian communities in California.
      Notebook also includes draft essays about Tassajara Zen Mountain Center and the United Farm Workers, as well as a review of Janwillem Van de Wetering, A Glimpse of Nothingness: Experiences in an American Zen Community (Boston: Houghton Mifflin St. Martin's Griffin, 1975). Also includes notes related to the custody of his daughter, Colorado M. Kagan (born 1969).
    - Original Images by Kagan
      Photographs by Kagan of sites and individuals related to utopian communities. A portion of images appeared in his New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community (New York: Penguin Books, 1975).
      Arranged chronologically.
      - Lama Foundation, 1968 August; (90 photographic prints) (Box 1, Folder 2-62)
        Biographical/Historical note
        Lama Foundation is a community in the mountains of north of Taos, New Mexico, founded in 1967 by Barbara Durkee and Stephen Durkee (later known as Asha Greer or Asha von Briesen and Nooruddeen Durkee).
      - Icaria Speranza, 1970 February; (24 negatives and 2 contact sheets) (Box 2, Folder 63)
        Jules Leroux and Armand DeHay established the egalitarian commune of Icaria Speranza in 1881 an area just south of Cloverdale, California. They had emigrated from an Icarian community in Iowa, Jeune Icarie, which had been founded on the principles set forth by in Étienne Cabet (1788-1856), Voyage en Icarie, published in 1840. The settlement dissolved by 1887.
      - Kaweah Colony, 1970 February; (12 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 64)
        The Kaweah Colony was a Marxian Socialist community settled in 1885 along the Kaweah River in the Sierras of eastern Tulare County by the Co-Operative Land Purchase and Colonization Association of California, led by Burnette G. Haskell and James J. Martin, labor activists from San Francisco. In 1890, the Kaweah colonists lost all claims to their land when Congress established the Sequoia National Park, and the community disbanded in 1892.
      - Krotona and Happy Valley School, 1970 March; (8 negatives and 3 contact sheets) (Box 2, Folder 65)
        Krotona, is a colony of the Adyar Theosophists in that settled in Hollywood, California, in 1912. The Krotona colony relocated to Ojai, California in 1926.
        In 1946, Jiddu Krishnamurti (1895-1986), Aldous Huxley (1894-1963), Guido Ferrando (1883-1969) and Rosalind Edith Rajagopal (1903-1996) established the Happy Valley School (later known as the Besant Hill School of Happy Valley) in Ojai.
      - Pisgah Grande, 1970 March; (83 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 66)
        Pisgah Grande (1914-1920) was a Pentecostal Christian community in Las Llajas Canyon of the Santa Susana Mountains, California, founded by Dr. Finis Ewing Yoakum (1851-1920). In 1920, James Cheek (born 1874), moved the colony to Pikesville, Tennessee.
      - Pisgah Grande and Fountain of the World, 1970 March; (12 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 67)
        The Fountain of the World, also known as the WKFL (Wisdom, Knowledge, Faith, Love) Foundation was founded circa 1948 by Krishna Venta (1911-1958, born Francis Heindswatzer Pencovic). The lodge for the Fountain of the World was located at Fountain of the World was located in Box Canyon, Canoga Park, California.
      - Fountain of the World, 1970 March; (12 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Ananda Ashrama, 1970 March; (37 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 69)
        Ananda Ashrama was a Vedanta center founded in La Crescenta, California in 1923 by Swami Paramananda (1884-1940).
      - Point Loma, 1970 March; (24 negatives and 2 contact sheets) (Box 2, Folder 70)
        In 1900 Katherine Tingley (1847-1929) moved the headquarters of the Theosophical Society to "Lomaland", a hilltop campus at Point Loma overlooking the ocean in San Diego, California. A theosophical commune developed, which included a Raja-Yoga school in 1900, open air theater in 1901, a college in 1914, and a theosophical university in 1919. The Theosophical Society moved to Covina, California in 1942.
      - Point Loma and Questhaven Retreat, 1970 March; (12 negatives, 1 contact sheet, and 4 photographic prints) (Box 2, Folder 71)
        Questhaven Retreat is a non-denominational Christian retreat in Escondido, California founded in 1940 by Christian mystic and spiritual teacher Flower A. Newhouse (1909-1994) and her husband, Lawrence George Newhouse (1910-1963).
      - Questhaven Retreat and Lemurian Fellowship, 1970 March; (12 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 72)
        The Lemurian Fellowship was created by Howard John Zitko (1911–2003) and Robert D. Stelle (1881-1952) in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, inspired by the work of Frederick Spencer Oliver (1866-1899). After a disagreement between them in 1946, Stelle relocated the Lemurian Fellowship to Ramona, California.
      - Lemurian Fellowship, 1970 March; (16 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - Fundación Indra Devi, 1970 March; (12 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 74)
        Indra Devi (1899-2002), born Eugenie Peterson, was a prominent yoga teacher. In 1961, she established the Fundación Indra Devi in Tecate, Mexico.
      - Self-Realization Golden World Colony, 1970 March; (24 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 75)
        Self-Realization Fellowship/Yogoda Satsanga Society of India is a spiritual organization founded in 1920 by Paramahansa Yogananda (1893-1952) and based in Los Angeles, California. The Self-Realization Golden World Colony, also known as a World Brotherhood Colony, in Encinitas, California, was a model community envisioned by Yogananda in 1937 and established by 1947.
      - Self-Realization Golden World Colony and Rosicrucian Fellowship, 1970 March; (12 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 76)
        The Rosicrucian Fellowship is an Esoteric Christian fraternal and service organization founded by Max Heindel (1865-1919) in 1909. In 1911, Heindel and his associates established the international headquarters of The Rosicrucian Fellowship on Mount Ecclesia in Oceanside, California.
      - Rosicrucian Fellowship, 1970 March; (12 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 77)
      - Rosicrucian Fellowship and Theosophical Society (Pasadena), 1970 March; (12 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 78)
        The Theosophical Society (Pasadena) is a successor organization to the original Theosophical Society founded by Helena Petrovna Blavatsky and others in New York City, 1875. In 1950-1951, the headquarters located to Pasadena, California.
      - Icaria Speranza, 1970 May; (12 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 2, Folder 79)
      - Krotona, 1970 July; (24 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 2, Folder 80)
      - Pisgah Grande, 1970 July; (26 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 81)
      - Krotona and Happy Valley School, 1971 January; (30 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 3, Folder 82)
      - Pisgah Faith Home, 1971 January; (36 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 83)
        Around 1900, Finis Ewing Yoakum (1851-1920), established Yoakum's Sanatorium at his house in the Highland Park neighborhood of Los Angeles, California. The home offered free care to indigents in the main home, as well as cottages, tents, and wagons on the property. By 1903, Yoakum's Sanatorium had became the Pisgah Faith Home.
      - Pisgah Faith Home and Vedanta Temple, Santa Barbara, 1971; (12 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Vedanta Temple, Santa Barbara, 1971 January; (12 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 3, Folder 85)
        In 1944, Spencer Kellogg donated thirty acres in Santa Barbara to the Vedanta Society of Southern California, which included a house, a small shrine and an art room. Since 1947, the site has served as a convent. The temple designed by Lutah Maria Riggs (1896-1984) was dedicated in 1956.
      - Vedanta Temple, Hollywood, 1971 January; (20 negatives and 2 contact sheets) (Box 3, Folder 86)
        In 1928, Carrie Mead Wyckoff (1859-1949) gave her home and property in Hollywood, California to Swami Prabhavananda (1893-1976) of the Ramakrishna Order of India. He moved there the following year from Portland, Oregon. In 1934, Prabhavananda established the Vedanta Society of Southern California as a non-profit organization. In 1938, the society completed and dedicated a temple on the property in Hollywood with money donated by Wyckoff.
      - Portraits of Bill Carrico?, 1971 May; (20 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 87)
        Bill Carrico? has a connection undocumented in the collection to the Esoteric Fraternity. In 1891, Hiram Erastus Butler (1841-1916) established the Esoteric Fraternity community in Applegate, California. The location also served as the headquarters for the Esoteric Publishing Co., which published books and journals, including The Esoteric: A Magazine of Advanced and Practical Esoteric Thought.
      - Esoteric Fraternity, 1972 February; (12 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 88)
      - Halcyon and Krotona, 1972 February; (22 negatives, 3 contact sheets, and 1 photographic print) (Box 3, Folder 89)
        Halcyon, California, is an intentional Theosophist community and headquarters of a religious organization, The Temple of the People. William Dower and Francia LaDue founded The Temple of the People in Syracuse, New York in 1898 and moved to Halcyon in 1903. Dower and LaDue also established the Halcyon Hotel and Sanatorium. Members of the community farmed and created handicrafts.
        Includes discrete portraits of Harold E. Forgostein (1906-1990), the guardian of the temple at Halcyon, and Betty Robertson Warrington (1887-1986), a librarian at Krotona and wife of Albert Powell Warrington (1866-1939), editor of the The American Theosophist.
      - Point Loma, 1972 February; (36 negatives, 4 contact sheets, and 2 photographic prints) (Box 3, Folder 90)
        Iverson Louis Harris (1890-1979) was secretary to Katherine Augusta Tingley (1847-1929) a prominent Theosophist and active in Theosophical Society since childhood. He served as Chairman of the Cabinet, 1942-1946. He then left the Theosophical Society over a disagreement about its leadership.
        Includes portraits of Harris and his then fiancée, Katherine Knoche McDonald (born circa 1905) at Point Loma.
      - Judith M. Tyberg, 1972 February; (12 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 3, Folder 91)
        Judith M. Tyberg (1902-1980), also known as Jyotipriya, was a scholar of Sanskrit and educated at the Theosophical Society's Point Loma Raja Yoga School and the Theosophical University. In 1953, she founded the East-West Cultural Center in Los Angeles, California, later known as the Sri Aurobindo Center of Los Angeles.
      - Happy Valley School, 1972 February 21; (15 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 3, Folder 92)
        Portraits of Rosalind Edith Rajagopal.
      - International Ideal City, 1972 July; (36 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 93)
        The International Ideal City, also known as the Creative Community Project, was a commune in Boonville, California. It was established by Sang Ik Choi, a missionary for the Unification Church.
      - International Re-Educational Foundation and Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, 1972 July; (12 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 3, Folder 94)
        International Re-Education Foundation in Oakland, California, was established by Sang Ik Choi, a missionary for the Unification Church.
        The Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, or Zenshinji (Zen Mind Temple), was established in Carmel Valley Village, California by the San Francisco Zen Center and abbot Shunryu Suzuki (1904-1971) in 1966.
      - Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, 1972 July; (36 negatives and 3 contact sheets) (Box 3, Folder 95)
      - Table Mountain Ranch, 1972 July; (12 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 96)
        Table Mountain Ranch is a commune established on 120 acres in Albion, California, in 1968.
      - Table Mountain Ranch and The Lord's Land, 1972 July; (12 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 97)
        The Lord's Land was a Christian commune founded in 1968 by Sabine Koritke Ball (1925-2009) in Albion, California.
      - The Lord's Land, 1972 July; (36 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 98)
      - Caspar Compound, 1972 July; (12 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 99)
        The Caspar Compound was a commune in Caspar, California.
      - "New World Utopias: The Search for Community in the West, 1876-1975", 1975 August-September; (96 negatives) (Box 3, Folder 100-101)
        Images of an exhibition by Kagan at the Oakland Museum of California, August 9-September 28, 1975, and sponsored by the California Historical Society.
      - Amish, 1976 January; (8 contact sheets and 11 photographic prints) (Box 3, Folder 102)
      - Lama Foundation, 1976 January; (108 negatives, 5 contact sheets, and 9 photographic prints) (Box 4, Folder 103)
      - The Farm, 1976 January; (482 negatives, 21 contact sheets, and 5 photographic prints) (Box 4, Folder 104)
        The Farm is an intentional community founded in 1971 by Stephen Gaskin (born 1935) near the town of Summertown, Tennessee.
      - Jean Nourse and Bernie Stevens, circa 1976; (12 negatives) (Box 4, Folder 105)
        Portraits of Nourse and Stevens, former members of the Llano Del Rio, a commune in Llano, California.
      - Ananda Ashrama, circa 1976; (12 negatives) (Box 4, Folder 106)
        Not the Vedanta center in La Crescenta, California.
      - Canning operation of Contadina in San Jose, California, circa 1976; (5 negatives) (Box 4, Folder 107)
      - Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, circa 1976; (7 contact prints and 39 photographic prints) (Box 5, Folder 108-111)
  - Oversize Photographic Prints by Kagan
    Oversize photograph prints, most 35.6 x 27.9 cm. and occasionally mounted on board, chiefly original images by Kagan of sites and individuals related to utopian communities.
    Arranged alphabetically by site, followed by a portrait of Bill Carrico? and images with unidentified locations.
    - Ananda Ashrama, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 112-118)
    - Fountaingrove, circa 1973 (Box 7, Folder 119-126)
      Fountaingrove was a utopian colony near Santa Rosa, California, founded by Thomas Lake Harris (1823-1906) in 1875. Most of its settlers were followers of Harris's Brotherhood of the New Life and relocated with Harris from their previous colony at Brocton, New York.
    - Fundación Indra Devi, 1970 March (Box 7, Folder 127)
    - Halcyon
      - The Temple of the People, 1972 February (Box 8, Folder 128-132)
      - Halcyon Hotel and Sanatorium, 1972 February (Box 8, Folder 133-137)
      - Cemetery, 1972 February (Box 8, Folder 138-139)
    - Holy City, circa 1972 (Box 9, Box 10, Folder 140-157)
    - Icaria Speranza, 1970 February (Box 11, Folder 158-161)
    - Kaweah, 1970 February (Box 11, Folder 162)
    - Krotona and Happy Valley School, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 163-165)
    - Lama Foundation, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 166)
    - Lemurian Fellowship, 1970 March (Box 11, Folder 167)
    - Llano Del Rio, circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 168-180)
    - Mesa Verde National Park, circa 1970-1975 (Box 12, Folder 181)
      View of Cliff Palace
    - Pisgah Faith Home, 1971 January (Box 13, Folder 182-188)
      Includes a view of the later home of Dr. Finis Ewing Yoakum at 140 South Avenue 59, Los Angeles, California
    - Pisgah Grande, 1970 (Box 14, Box 15, Folder 189-208)
    - Point Loma, 1970-1972 (Box 16, Folder 209-211)
    - Questhaven Retreat, 1970 March (Box 16, Folder 212-214)
    - Rosicrucian Fellowship, 1970 March (Box 16, Folder 215-219)
    - Self-Realization Golden World Colony, 1970 March (Box 16, Folder 220A-C)
    - Theosophical Society (Pasadena), 1970 March (Box 17, Folder 221)
    - Portrait of Bill Carrico?, 1971 March (Box 17, Folder 222)
    - Unidentified locations (Box 17, Folder 223-224)
      Includes images of an apartment building, a rocking chair in front of a wooden building, forect scene, and a copy photograph of a woman.
  - Copy Photographs
    Copy photographs chiefly created by Kagan from original photographs held by individuals and repositories, as well as from publications. The majority of images appeared in his New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community.